Maria Korochkina, PhD

I am a cognitive neuroscientist studying language and memory, with **advanced technical skills** in data analysis and statistics. I have a strong commitment to **open science** and am actively involved in promoting transparency and reproducibility in research. I am passionate about **making research accessible** to the wider community and strive to **engage diverse voices in research** to drive meaningful societal change.

Education and qualifications

- PhD in Cognitive Science
 Joint degree from Macquarie University (Australia) and Universities of Potsdam (Germany),
 Newcastle upon Tyne (UK), Groningen (Netherlands), Trento (Italy), IDEALAB PhD programme

 2021 Badged Instructor, The Carpentries

 2015 − 2018 MSc in Experimental and Clinical Linguistics
- University of Potsdam, Germany, IECL programme
 2010 2015 BA & MA in Philology

Lomonosov Moscow State University, Russia

Academic employment

o6/2022 – ongoing
o2/2020 – o6/2022
o7/2016 – o8/2018

■ Postdoctoral Research Fellow, Rastle Lab, Royal Holloway, University of London, UK
Academic Tutor, Macquarie University, Australia

Research Assistant, NOLA Lab & Vasishth Lab, University of Potsdam, Germany

Teaching and educating

- 10/07/2024 Invited speaker, 31st annual meeting of the Society for the Scientific Study of Reading Workshop "Opening up Open Science: Nuts and Bolts for Beginners" Pre-registration & Open Materials: The What, Why, & How 10/06/2024 Invited speaker, Festival of Research, Royal Holloway, University of London ReproducibiliTea journal club: Fostering open science and reproducible research 27/03/2023 **Workshop instructor**, Royal Holloway, University of London Bayesian Linear Mixed Effects and Distributional Regression models with brms 7/11/2022 – ongoing ■ Instructor, ReproducibiliTea journal club, Royal Holloway, University of London 02/2020 - 06/2022 **Academic Tutor**, Macquarie University Session 1, 2021 & 2022: Design and Statistics III Session 2, 2020 & 2021: Design and Statistics II Session 2, 2020 & 2021: Acquired Speech and Language Disorders
 - Session 2, 2020 & 2021: Design and Statistics II

 Session 2, 2020 & 2021: Acquired Speech and Language Disorders

 Session 1, 2020: Exp Design and Data Analysis for the Cognitive and Brain Sciences

 Workshop instructor, Macquarie University

 Data analysis using (generalised) linear mixed effects models in R
 - 21–25/09/2020 Co-instructor, Introduction to R Software Carpentry workshop, Macquarie University

Publications

Pre-registrations, data, materials, analysis code, and pre-prints for all papers are available on OSF (https://osf.io/zf8px/).

Pre-prints under review

Korochkina, M., & Rastle, K. (2024a). The vocabulary barrier in the General Certificate of Secondary Education (GCSE) in English Literature [Pre-print]. https://doi.org/10.31219/osf.io/vg8c3

Peer-reviewed

- Crawford, M., Raheel, N., **Korochkina**, **M.**, & Rastle, K. (In press). Inadequate foundational decoding skills constrain global literacy goals for pupils in low- and middle-income countries. *Nature Human Behaviour*. https://osf.io/preprints/psyarxiv/2qxm9
- **Korochkina**, M., Marelli, M., Brysbaert, M., & Rastle, K. (2024). The Children and Young People's Books Lexicon (CYP-LEX): A large-scale lexical database of books read by children and young people in the United Kingdom [Published online ahead of print]. *Quarterly Journal of Experimental Psychology*. https://doi.org/10.1177/17470218241229694
- **Korochkina**, M., Nickels, L., & Bürki, A. (2024). What can we learn about integration of novel words into semantic memory from automatic semantic priming? *Language, Cognition, and Neuroscience*, 39(4), 455–488. https://doi.org/10.1080/23273798.2024.2328586
- Lombard, A., Ulicheva, A., **Korochkina**, **M.**, & Rastle, K. (2024). The regularity of polysemy patterns in the mind: Computational and experimental data. *GLOSSA Psycholinguistics*, *3*(1), 3, 1–24. https://doi.org/10.5070/G60111327
- **Korochkina**, **M.**, Sowman, P., Nickels, L., & Bürki, A. (2023). Neural correlates of encoding in novel word learning. *Collabra: Psychology*, *9*(1), 57525. https://doi.org/10.1525/collabra.57525
- **Korochkina**, **M.**, Bürki, A., & Nickels, L. (2021). Apples and oranges: How does learning context affect novel word learning? *Journal of Memory and Language*, 120, 104246. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jml.2021.104246

Theses

Korochkina, M. (2022a). Learning of new words: Behavioural and electrophysiological correlates of encoding and integration [PhD thesis]. Macquarie University. https://doi.org/10.25949/23707128.v1

Outreach contributions

Publications

- Korochkina, M., & Rastle, K. (2024b). What makes GCSE English Literature so hard for students?, Tes Magazine. https://www.tes.com/magazine/teaching-learning/secondary/what-makes-gcse-english-lit-so-hard-students
- **Korochkina**, **M.**, & Rastle, K. (2024c). What words do children encounter when they read for pleasure? [Also available on https://www.rastlelab.com/post/what-words-do-children-encounter-when-they-read-for-pleasure], Nomanis, Issue 27. https://www.nomanis.com.au/blog/issue-17-june-2024

Talks

Korochkina, M. (2024d, June). What does it take to read and understand the GCSE English Literature texts? Working Together: Research and Practice event 2024, The South East Research Network for Schools, Egham, UK. https://www.royalholloway.ac.uk/research-and-teaching/departments-and-schools/psychology/research/serns/serns-events/2024/

Korochkina, M., & Rastle, K. (2024d, September). Words in books: A challenge, a blessing, or both? (Invited talk). ResearchED National Conference, London, UK.

https://researched.org.uk/event/researched-national-conference-2024/

Academic and administrative service

Reviewer for Psychonomic Bulletin & Review; Behavior Research Meth-Peer-review ods; Journal of Memory and Language; Language, Cognition, & Neuroscience; Advances in Cognitive Psychology; Language and Speech; Psychology & Neuroscience, Applied Psycholinguistics

Organiser, ReproducibiliTea journal club Open science Royal Holloway, University of London

Equality, diversity, & inclusion Postdoc representative in a successful bid for the Athena Swan Silver award, Royal Holloway, University of London

Awards and funding

Student Researcher Credibility Prize, The British Neuroscience Association 2023 Read the media announcement here.

Funding award for an 8-week Instructor Training with The Carpentries, Macquarie University 2021

2020 **Postgraduate Research Fund**, Macquarie University

2019-2022 **■ International Research Excellence PhD Scholarship**, Macquarie University

2019 Conference travel & participant recruitment awards, University of Potsdam

PhD Scholarship, University of Potsdam 2018-2019

2012 & 2014 **Student exchange awards**, University of Vienna, Austria

Scientific societies

- The British Neuroscience Association
- The Experimental Psychology Society
- Society for the Scientific Study of Reading
- The European Society for Cognitive Psychology
- The Psychonomic Society

Skills

Experimental techniques Behavioural, eye-tracking, fNIRS, EEG

Corpus linguistics, computational modelling

Programming languages & software

MATLAB, Python, R, Stan, Presentation Neurobehavioural Systems Stata, HTML, OpenSesame, LATEX

English, German, Russian, Swedish, Icelandic (beginner) Languages British Sign Language (beginner)

Conference contributions

Slide decks for all talks and posters are available on my website (https://mariakna.github.io).

Selected talks

- **Korochkina**, M. (2024b, July). The nature of morphemic regularities in children's literature: What do British children learn about derivational morphology when they read? Talk given at the 31st annual meeting of the Society for the Scientific Study of Reading, Copenhagen, Denmark.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2024c, July). What can children learn about English morphology through book reading? Talk given at the annual meeting of the Experimental Psychology Society, York, UK.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2023a, September). *Apples and oranges: How does learning context affect novel word learning?* Talk given at the Contextual Diversity Workshop organised by the Experimental Psychology Society, London, UK.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2023b, January). *Behavioural and electrophysiological markers of integration in novel word learning*. Talk given at the annual meeting of the Experimental Psychology Society, London, UK.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2023c, September). *The Children and Young People's Books Lexicon (CYP-LEX): A lexical database of books directed at children and young adults*. Talk given at the 23rd meeting of the European Society for Cognitive Psychology, Porto, Portugal.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2023d, July). The Children and Young People's Books Lexicon (CYP-LEX): How does book language change as children transition into and through adolescence? Talk given at the annual meeting of the Experimental Psychology Society, Swansea, UK.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2023e, September). What do children read as they transition into and through adolescence? Insights from CYP-LEX, a new large-scale lexicon of books for children and young people. Talk given at the annual meeting of the Cognitive and Developmental sections of the British Psychological Society, Bristol, UK.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2021, October). Behavioural and electrophysiological markers of integration in novel word learning. Talk given at the annual meeting of the Society for the Neurobiology of Language, online attendance.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2020a, October). *A behavioural and electrophysiological investigation of novel word learning*. Talk given at the Words in the World conference, online attendance.

Posters

- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2024a, November). Learning in the wild: What can children learn about morphemic statistical regularities through reading? Poster to be presented at the 65th annual meeting of the Psychonomic Society, New York City, USA.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2022b, September). Neural correlates of encoding in learning of novel names for novel concepts. Poster presented at the Architectures & Mechanisms for Language Processing conference, York, UK.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2020b, November). *Behavioural and electrophysiological markers of integration in novel word learning*. Poster presented at the 61st annual meeting of the Psychonomic Society, online attendance.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2019a, September). *The effect of the learning context on novel word learning*. Poster presented at the Architectures & Mechanisms for Language Processing conference, Moscow, Russia.
- **Korochkina**, **M.** (2019b, September). *Semantic integration of new vocabulary: Does learning context matter?* Poster presented at the 21st meeting of the European Society for Cognitive Psychology, Tenerife, Spain.

Further training and development

2022 Introduction to Natural Language Processing in Python DataCamp

■ The 6th Summer School on Statistical Methods for Linguistics and Psychology

Bayesian Advanced Track University of Potsdam

2020 Getting Started with Python

Python Data Structures

MOOC, University of Michigan

MATLAB Fundamentals

A MathWorks workshop, Macquarie University

■ Python Basics for Data Science

edX

■ Understanding the Brain: The Neurobiology of Everyday Life

MOOC, University of Chicago

2019 Australasian Magnetoencephalography (WAM)

Workshop on the Neurocognitive clinical applications of MEG: Present and future Macquarie University

■ Introduction to Python

Software Carpentry Workshop, Macquarie University

■ The 3rd Summer School on Statistical Methods for Linguistics and Psychology

Bayesian Advanced Track University of Potsdam

2018 Advanced Methods: Bayesian Statistics with R

Workshop, University of Potsdam

2017 NIRS-Workshop

NIRx Medizintechnik GmbH, Berlin

2016 NIRS-Workshop

NIRx Medizintechnik GmbH, Berlin

■ Standardised Tests of Cognitive and Language Development in Children

Workshop, University of Potsdam